

Developing and Supporting Legal Information Specialists
Perfectionnement et soutien des spécialistes de l'information juridique

October 8, 2017

Multi-Stakeholder Forum Selection Committee Canadian Open Government Civil Society Network join@opengovdialogue.ca

Dear Selection Committee Members,

I am writing to nominate Sarah Sutherland to the Canadian Open Government Civil Society Network's Mutil-Stakeholder Forum as a representative of the Canadian Association of Law Libraries / Association canadienne des bibliothèques de droit (CALL/ACBD), a registered Canadian not-for-profit organization.

CALL/ACBD seeks to have the interests of the users of legal information in Canada, including the legal profession, law schools, judiciary, and general public, represented in the Network's discussions. We have asked Sarah to represent the association, because her experience working at the Canadian Legal Information Institute (CanLII) makes her an excellent addition to the group.

CanLII is a non-profit publisher of legal information, which makes extensive use of government information in the form of court and tribunal decisions and legislation. These are then made available for the public through their website canlii.org. Legal documents, especially court decisions require some special consideration in any discussion of open data, because they are public yet many of them include very private information. They are also government documents that many companies have used to build business generating significant income.

These are important considerations in any public discussion of a national discussion of open data. And Sarah would be an excellent representative to ensure that the interests of the legal community and litigants are considered as part of the larger discussion about open government.

She is actively engaged with the national legal information community, and regularly publishes and speaks in local and national venues.

Here is an example of an article Sarah wrote:

"Some Thoughts on the Accessibility of Legal Information and Legal Records", *Slaw: Canada's Online Legal Magazine*, February 16, 2016, http://www.slaw.ca/2016/02/16/some-thoughts-on-the-accessibility-of-legal-information-and-legal-records/.

Please feel free to forward any questions you may have about this submission.

Yours sincerely,

Jennifer Walker Secretary, CALL/ACBD Head Librarian, County of Carleton Law Association

CC Ann Marie Melvie, President CALL/ACBD

Sarah Sutherland

Manager, Content and Partnerships
Canadian Legal Information Institute (CanLII)
Vancouver, BC

Profile

Experienced information professional and manager, with a vision on how to use technological solutions in ways that leverage emerging opportunities to build valuable tools and improve the ways people work. Believes in volunteering as a way to create connections and build stronger communities.

Education

Master of Business Administration | University of British Columbia, Vancouver, B.C. 2019 (anticipated)

Master of Library & Information Studies | University of British Columbia, Vancouver, B.C. 2005

Bachelor of Arts, English Major | University of British Columbia, Vancouver, B.C. 1998

Professional experience

Manager, Content and Partnerships

June 2013 - present

CanLII (Canadian Legal Information Institute) | Vancouver, BC

- Coordinated site development and managed community development for CanLII Connects
 (http://canliiconnects.org), an award winning legal research tool and legal social networking site that generates over 90,000 visits per month, with over 45,000 pieces of crowd sourced commentary submitted by the legal community
- Write, present, and manage social media tools to successfully compete in mind share with commercial organizations with substantial advertising budgets, and persuade the community about the social value of legal information
- Research and advise on technological and business developments to illuminate CanLII's decision making process, including online community development, search engine optimization, API functionality, emerging data standards, trends in legal publishing, and the wider legal industry
- Collaborate with external technology suppliers to implement large development projects and ongoing management of custom applications

Adjunct Professor

May 2014 – present

University of British Columbia | Vancouver, BC

 Taught "Legal Information Sources and Services" as part of the master of library and information studies at the School of Library, Archives, and information studies in 2014 and 2016

Professional experience (cont.)

Manager, Library Services

McMillan LLP | Vancouver, BC

November 2010 – May 2013

- Increased the value of the library to the firm, leading to a raised profile for the library and an increase in staffing levels to meet the new needs
- Integrated local knowledge assets into the national knowledge management program
- Managed the migration of two legacy library systems into a new integrated library system from software selection including data migration, and staff training
- Supervised one professional and one paraprofessional staff members

Manager, Library Network Development Interoperability Librarian

January 2010 – October 2010 September 2009 – January 2010

Provincial Library and Literacy Office (PLLO), Ministry of Education, Government of Saskatchewan | Regina, SK

- Acted as PLLO lead for the government funded, province wide integrated library system project, which moved all public libraries to a single system with a shared catalogue and circulation, worked with staff of public libraries and the PLLO to ensure government interests related to policy, bibliographic control, interface, information technology hardware and software, training, and implementation were addressed
- Liaised between public libraries and the Ministry of Education network staff to ensure the province wide-area-network upgrade to fibre was on track to connect underserviced rural public libraries
- Developed a plan to automate several branch libraries in three regional library systems into the new province-wide ILS, including addressing data upgrades, staff training, and network connectivity issues
- Managed the migration to the new integrated library system for PLLO data and staff, making sure
 policy and technical requirements were met and ensuring staff were involved in the process to
 ensure acceptance of the change
- Supervised a team of unionized professional and paraprofessional staff who provided technical services to the public library system

Head, NRC Information Centre Saskatoon

July 2006 - August 2009

Canadian Institute for Scientific and Technical Information, National Research Council of Canada | Saskatoon, SK

- Integrated the information centre into administrative and research processes at the
 research institute where it was not integrated before, including participation in planning
 meetings, increasing role in developing the research program, and a greater value being
 placed on the value of information services
- Implemented the national Competitive Technical Intelligence program in Saskatchewan providing intelligence to the research institute and regional biotechnology sector with a technical business analyst
- Initiated successful information services including current awareness emails subscribed to by approximately 25% of institute staff and voluntary information literacy training attended by approximately 80% of institute staff
- Supervised one unionized paraprofessional staff member, together we worked towards helping her develop skills and making her workflow more efficient

Professional experience (cont.)

Saskatoon Librarian (term) June 2005 - July 2006

Law Society of Saskatchewan Libraries | Saskatoon, SK

- Managed the Law Society Library in the Court of Queen's Bench, including providing reference, professional research services, and user training
- Coordinated copy editing, fact checking, and indexing of a history of the law society, working with internal staff and an external editor to ensure success of the project
- Implemented a retrospective conversion project to catalogue the library's government documents
- Supervised two paraprofessional staff members

Volunteer activities

Alcuin Society

Vice chair and board member 2015 - present

Decoda Literacy Solutions

Advisor on IT and libraries 2012 - present

The Foundation for Legal Knowledge Based Systems

Program Committee Member, Jurix: 27th, 28th, 29th, & 30th International Conferences on Legal Knowledge and Information Systems

2014, 2015, 2016, 2017

Canadian Association of Law Libraries (CALL-ACBD)

Member – KF Modified Committee 2011 - present CALL-ACBD Statistician 2012 - 2016

British Columbia Library Association

Member at large 2015 - 2017

Vancouver Association of Law Libraries

Vice-President/President/Past President 2012 - 2015

Selected publications

Bi-Monthly Column on Legal Information, *Slaw.ca: Canada's Online Legal Magazine*, http://www.slaw.ca/author/sutherland.

Representative titles:

KF Modified Linked Data Research Project, report to the CALL-ACBD Committee to Promote Research, May 5, 2016, http://www.callacbd.ca/resources/Documents/Knight%20KFModifiedProject-report-final.pdf.

[&]quot;Quantifying the Value of Legal Information"

[&]quot;Legal Research's Easy Button Moment"

[&]quot;Some Thoughts on the Accessibility of Legal Information and Legal Records"

[&]quot;Moving Closer to Organizations' Core Businesses"

[&]quot;How Will We Find What's Outside Our Walled Gardens?"

[&]quot;Law Libraries, Data, Value, and Story Telling"

[&]quot;What Technical Skills Should We All Really Be Learning?"

[&]quot;Where Will Old, Expensive, or Unexpected Legal Information Come From When Libraries All Downsize Together?"

Selected publications (cont.)

"Saving the Irreplaceable in Small Libraries," Amphora (Alcuin Society), no.165, (2013): 23-6.

"Law Firm Changes Offer Opportunities for Libraries: Suggestions for Getting Ahead of the Curve," *AALL Spectrum* (American Association of Law Libraries) 17, no. 6, (2013): 15-7, http://www.aallnet.org/main-menu/Publications/spectrum/Archives/vol-17/No-6/law-firm-changes.pdf.

"Why We Need Business Analysis to Go With our Project Management," *Canadian Law Library Review* 37, no. 3, 125-6.

"On Hiring Library Staff in Rural Areas," *Partnership: the Canadian Journal of Library and Information Practice and Research* 6, no. 2 (2011), http://journal.lib.uoguelph.ca/index.php/perj/article/view/1540.

Presentations

"Navigating Linked Open Data: a Panel Discussion." Presented with Tim Knight, Osgoode Hall Law Library, York University, and Christina Harlow, University of Tennessee, at the Access Conference, Toronto ON, September 2015.

"Supporting Business Development Goals – Moving Toward a Course of Action in Public, Academic, and Private Libraries." Presented with Alyssa Green, Vancouver Public Library, at the British Columbia Library Association Conference, Richmond BC, May 2015.

"A Conversation on the Semantic Web and Legal Information." Pre-conference workshop presented with Tim Knight Osgoode Hall Law Library, York University at the Canadian Association of Law Libraries Conference, Winnipeg MB, May 2014, http://yorkspace.library.yorku.ca/xmlui/handle/10315/27526.

"Legal Research in a Nutshell." Presented with Carolyn Petrie, Bull Housser Tupper LLP, at the British Columbia Library Association Conference, Richmond BC, May 2013.

"Library System Migrations: If Your Staff Want to Retire, You're Doing It Wrong." Presented at Canadian Association of Law Libraries Conference, Toronto ON, May 2012.

Awards and scholarships

2016 Education Reserve Grant

Canadian Association of Law Libraries | Awarded to fund tuition at the master of business administration program at the University of British Columbia

2016 Peter Bark Memorial Bursary

Vancouver Association of Law Libraries | Awarded to fund tuition at the master of business administration program at the University of British Columbia

2014 Peter Bark Memorial Bursary

Vancouver Association of Law Libraries | Awarded to fund attendance at Access Conference 2014, September 29-October 2, 2014, Calgary AB

2013 Research Grant

Canadian Association of Law Libraries | To fund a project to explore the Linked Data Application of KF Modified Classification in collaboration with Tim Knight, Head of Technical Services, Osgoode Hall Law Library, York University

References

Xavier Beauchamp-Tremblay President and CEO

CanLII (Canadian Legal Information Institute / Institut canadien d'information juridique)

World Exchange Plaza 1810 – 45 O'Connor Street Ottawa, Ontario K1P 1A4

Ann Marie Melvie President Canadian Association of Law Libraries / Association canadienne des bibliothèques de droit 2425 Victoria Avenue Regina, SK S4P 4W6